Tamzin: It's very important that young
people talk about their problems,
even if it's not just not with us
as a mental health service, but with
maybe school as well, like pastoral
support at school or even family.
Fran: When someone is very
young they are still developing.
So identifying exactly what's going on
for them can be a little bit difficult
and it's more about what can you help
them to learn to sort of cope with?
Tamzin: If they're not talking
about their problems, then you don't
know what else it's going into.
So if someone's not sharing it and
talking about it, they could be hiding
it and they could end up, especially
young people we work with, they
could end up taking their own life.
Fran: There'll be a lot of the time
people diagnosing and trying to
label kids with certain disorders.
When a lot of the time I think it
was just childhood development.
Tamzin: So we've got - we've worked
with young people who - well,
I - in the past have worked with
young people in the care system.
So they're young people that have been
in care for maybe quite a lot of their
lives, but they're only kind of finding
out that their identity maybe when
they're kind of late, leaving school.
So they're young people are kind of better
to come to us for therapy and work when
they are that age, when they left school.
Fran: I think anxiety and depression
are very common and there's very
common -  elements of them are
very common in young people, and
then very common in old people.
So I think that I just try and work
with what I can see there rather than
saying, "oh, this person doesn't have
anxiety or this person doesn't have
depression" because I think that, I think
most of them will have elements of it
and there's ways we can still help them.
Tamzin: They might have this mindset
of, "I don't want to talk about
it it's just going to go away."
But I think we want young people
who can talk and share their
problems because if they don't then
things can escalate and then the
problems can be a lot, a lot worse.
And we find that they're in a really bad
state and they might not be able to get
help because they're in that dire state.
Fran: You know, I think there's levels
when it gets to a point as well when
you might notice with a young person
that they, you know, say anxiety with a
13, 14 year old, it might just be that
they're going into school everyday,
it's quite anxiety provoking, or you
do notice when it's something worse
than that and it's quite chronic.
And I think at that point you can
differentiate just in terms of if
it's affecting every area of their
life and preventing them from doing
things that they'd like to do.
Then I would say that's when it's
moving towards being more chronic.
Tamzin: So if they're like troubled and
they've got things going on, it's better
to share and talk about it because if,
we find, you know, the more we get in
people that are engaging with us and the
more they talk to us, the more we can
help and support them to stop feeling
like that and stop feeling low or stop
being suicidal or stop self-harming.